Have you ever wondered
هل تساءلتم يوما
what is inside your dental plaque?
عما يوجد داخل طبقة البلاك الموجودة بأسنانكم؟
Probably not, but people like me do.
غالبا لا، لكن الناس أمثالي يتساءلون
I'm an archeological geneticist
أنا باحثة في ميدان علم الوراثة الأثرية
at the Center for Evolutionary Medicine
في مركز الطب التطوري
at the University of Zurich,
،في جامعة زيوريخ
and I study the origins and evolution of human health and disease
وأدرس نشأة وتطور الأمراض والصحة البشرية
by conducting genetic research
عن طريق إجراء أبحاث وراثية
on the skeletal and mummified remains of ancient humans.
على بقايا عظام ومحنطات البشر القدماء
And through this work, I hope to better understand
ومن خلال هذا العمل، آمل إلى التوصل إلى فهم أفضل
the evolutionary vulnerabilities of our bodies,
لأوجه الضعف في تطور أجسادنا
so that we can improve
حتى نتمكن من تطوير
and better manage our health in the future.
.وتحسين كيفية الإعتناء بصحتنا في المستقبل
There are different ways to approach evolutionary medicine,
,هناك طرق مختلفة لدراسة الطب التطوري
and one way is to extract human DNA
إحدى الطرق هي استخلاص الحمض النووي البشري
from ancient bones.
.من العظام القديمة
And from these extracts,
،ومن هذه العينات
we can reconstruct the human genome at different points in time
يمكننا إعادة تشكيل الجينوم البشري في مراحل مختلفة من الزمان
and look for changes that might be related to adaptations,
،والبحث عن التغيرات التي قد تكون ذات صلة بالتكيف
risk factors and inherited diseases.
.وعوامل الخطر والأمراض الموروثة
But this is only one half of the story.
.ولكن هذا هو نصف القصة فقط
The most important health challenges today
إن أهم التحديات الصحية اليوم
are not caused by simple mutations in our genome,
،لم تنشأ نتيجة تغيرات بسيطة في جيناتنا
but rather result from a complex and dynamic interplay
إنما عن تأثيرات ديناميكية ومعقدة
between genetic variation,
،بين التباين الجيني
diet, microbes and parasites
النظام الغذائي، الجراثيم والطفيليات
and our immune response.
.والاستجابة المناعية لأجسادنا
All of these diseases
كل هذه الأمراض
have a strong evolutionary component
تحمل عنصرا تطوريا قويا
that directly relates to the fact
يتصل مباشرة بواقع
that we live today in a very different environment
أننا نعيش اليوم في بيئة مختلفة جداً
than the ones in which our bodies evolved.
.عن تلك التي تطورت فيها أجسادنا
And in order to understand these diseases,
،ولكي نفهم هذه الأمراض
we need to move past studies of the human genome alone
إننا بحاجة إلى تجاوز دراسات الجينوم البشري وحدها
and towards a more holistic approach
و التوجه نحو مقاربة أكثر شمولية
to human health in the past.
.للحالة الصحية للإنسان في الماضي
But there are a lot of challenges for this.
.ولكن هناك الكثير من التحديات
And first of all, what do we even study?
ولكن أولاً وقبل كل شيء، ما الذي ندرسه؟
Skeletons are ubiquitous; they're found all over the place.
.الهياكل منتشرة؛ نجدها في كل مكان
But of course, all of the soft tissue has decomposed,
،ولكن وبطبيعة الحال، كل الأنسجة الرخوة قد تحللت
and the skeleton itself
والهيكل العظمي نفسه
has limited health information.
.يحمل معلومات صحية محدودة
Mummies are a great source of information,
،تشكل المومياءات مصدرا كبيرا للمعلومات
except that they're really geographically limited
إلا أنها محدودة جغرافيا
and limited in time as well.
.ومحدودة في الزمان كذلك
Coprolites are fossilized human feces,
،الكوبرولايت هو براز بشري متحجر
and they're actually extremely interesting.
وهو مهم للغاية
You can learn a lot about ancient diet and intestinal disease,
،يمكنك أن تعرف الكثير عن النظم الغذائية القديمة والأمراض المعوية
but they are very rare.
.لكنها نادرة جداً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So to address this problem,
،و لمعالجة هذه المشكلة
I put together a team of international researchers
جمعت فريقا من الباحثين العالميين
in Switzerland, Denmark and the U.K.
من سويسرا والدنمارك والمملكة المتحدة
to study a very poorly studied, little known material
لدراسة مادة لم تدرس إلا قليلا
that's found on people everywhere.
.ونجدها عند الناس في كل مكان
It's a type of fossilized dental plaque
إنها نوع من بلاك الأسنان المتحجر
that is called officially dental calculus.
.والتي تسمى رسميا جير الأسنان
Many of you may know it by the term tartar.
.العديد منكم قد يعرفها تحت مصطلح اصفرار الاسنان
It's what the dentist cleans off your teeth
وهي ما ينظفه طبيب الأسنان من أسنانكم
every time that you go in for a visit.
.خلال كل زيارة
And in a typical dentistry visit,
،في زيارة عادية لطبيب الأسنان
you may have about 15 to 30 milligrams removed.
.قد يتم إزالة حوالي 15 إلى 30 مليغرام
But in ancient times before tooth brushing,
.ولكن في العصور القديمة و قبل إستخدام فرشاة الأسنان
up to 600 milligrams might have built up on the teeth
قد يتراكم 600 مليغرام من الجيرعلى الأسنان
over a lifetime.
.على مدى فترة حياة
And what's really important about dental calculus
وما هو مهم في جير الأسنان
is that it fossilizes just like the rest of the skeleton,
،هو أنه يتحجر تماما مثل بقية الهيكل العظمي
it's abundant in quantity before the present day
وقد وجد بوفرة قبل يومنا هذا
and it's ubiquitous worldwide.
.وما زال موجودا في جميع أنحاء العالم
We find it in every population around the world at all time periods
نجدها في كل سكان العالم و في جميع الفترات الزمنية
going back tens of thousands of years.
.رجوعا عشرات الآلاف من السنين إلى الوراء
And we even find it in neanderthals and animals.
.ونجدها حتى في الانسان البدائي والحيوانات
And so previous studies
وقد قامت الدراسات السابقة
had only focused on microscopy.
.بالتركيز على الفحص المجهري فقط
They'd looked at dental calculus under a microscope,
فقد عاينوا جير الأسنان تحت المجهر
and what they had found was things like pollen
و عثروا على أشياء مثل حبوب الطلع
and plant starches,
،ونشا النباتات
and they'd found muscle cells from animal meats
ووجدوا خلايا عضلية من اللحوم الحيوانية
and bacteria.
.وجراثيم
And so what my team of researchers, what we wanted to do,
ما أردنا فعله كفريق باحثين
is say, can we apply
هو بحث إمكانية تطبيق
genetic and proteomic technology
التكنولوجيا الوراثية و البروتينية
to go after DNA and proteins,
،للبحث عن حمض نووي وبروتينات
and from this can we get better taxonomic resolution
وهل يمكننا الحصول على معلومات أفضل
to really understand what's going on?
لنفهم بحق ما يجري؟
And what we found
وما وجدناه هو أنه يمكننا
is that we can find many commensal and pathogenic bacteria
أن نجد الكثير من الجراثيم التكافلية أو الممرضة
that inhabited the nasal passages and mouth.
.التي سكنت ممرات الأنف والفم
We also have found immune proteins
كما وجدنا بروتينات مناعية
related to infection and inflammation
متصلة بالعدوى والإلتهاب
and proteins and DNA related to diet.
.وبروتينات وحمض نووي ذات صلة بالنظام الغذائي
But what was surprising to us, and also quite exciting,
،ولكن ما كان مفاجئاً لنا، ومثيرا في نفس الوقت
is we also found bacteria
هو أننا وجدنا بكتيريا
that normally inhabit upper respiratory systems.
.تسكن عادة أعلى الجهاز التنفسي
So it gives us virtual access to the lungs,
،لذا فإنها تعطينا نظرة افتراضية داخل الرئتين
which is where many important diseases reside.
.حيث تكمن كثير من الأمراض المهمة
And we also found bacteria
ووجدنا أيضا بكتريا
that normally inhabit the gut.
.تسكن عادة في الأمعاء
And so we can also now virtually gain access
فإنه يمكننا الآن أيضا الوصول
to this even more distant organ system
إلى ذالك النظام الأكثر بعدا
that, from the skeleton alone,
،كل ذلك من الهيكل العظمي وحده
has long decomposed.
.الذي قد تحلل منذ وقت طويل
And so by applying ancient DNA sequencing
فبتطبيق سلاسل الحمض النووي القديم
and protein mass spectrometry technologies
وتقنيات دراسة الطيف الكتلي للبروتين
to ancient dental calculus,
،لجير الأسنان القديم
we can generate immense quantities of data
يمكننا أن نستخرج كميات هائلة من البيانات
that then we can use to begin to reconstruct a detailed picture
ثم نستخدمها للبدء في إعادة بناء
of the dynamic interplay
صورة مفصلة للتفاعل الديناميكي
between diet, infection and immunity
بين الغذاء والمرض والمناعة
thousands of years ago.
. قبل آلاف السنين
So what started out as an idea,
،فما بدأ كفكرة
is now being implemented
يتم حاليا تنفيذه
to churn out millions of sequences
لإصدار الملايين من المتواليات
that we can use to investigate
التي يمكن أن نستخدمها للتحقيق
the long-term evolutionary history of human health and disease,
،في التاريخ الطويل لتطور صحة الإنسان وأمراضه
right down to the genetic code of individual pathogens.
.وصولا إلى الصيغة الجينية لمسببات الأمراض
And from this information
ومن خلال هذه المعلومات
we can learn about how pathogens evolve
يمكننا تعلم الكيفية التي تتطور فيها مسببات المرض
and also why they continue to make us sick.
.وأيضا لماذا تستمر في إمراضنا
And I hope I have convinced you
وآمل أني قد أقنعتكم
of the value of dental calculus.
بقيمة جير الأسنان
And as a final parting thought,
،و كفكرة وداع نهائية
on behalf of future archeologists,
،ونيابة عن علماء الآثارفي المستقبل
I would like to ask you to please think twice
أود أن أطلب منكم التفكير مرتين
before you go home and brush your teeth.
.قبل العودة إلى منازلكم و تنظيف أسنانكم بالفرشاة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
.شكرا